<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The mystery of the vialls opened: being a short exposition upon the pouring out of the four last vialls, mentioned in the 16 chapter of the Revelation: wherein divers things relating to times present, past, and to come, are discovered: as the ruine of Antichrist, and the severall degrees thereunto; and the shadowing out these times wherein we live, are generally surveyed.</title>
            <author>Parker, John, 1564-1614.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91429</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P451</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E609_19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16504</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860045</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860045</idno>
            <idno type="VID">112152</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91429)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 112152)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 93:E609[19])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The mystery of the vialls opened: being a short exposition upon the pouring out of the four last vialls, mentioned in the 16 chapter of the Revelation: wherein divers things relating to times present, past, and to come, are discovered: as the ruine of Antichrist, and the severall degrees thereunto; and the shadowing out these times wherein we live, are generally surveyed.</title>
                  <author>Parker, John, 1564-1614.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>15, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for John Sweeting at the Angel in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"The mystery of the vialls opened" signed: Mr. Parker.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug: 21 1650"; the 1 in imprint date has been crossed out.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Revelation XVI --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible --  Prophecies --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:112152:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE MYSTERY OF THE VIALLS OPENED: Being a ſhort Expoſition upon the pouring out of the four laſt VIALLS, mentioned in the 16 Chapter of the <hi>REVELATION:</hi> Wherein divers things relating to times preſent, paſt, and to come, are diſcovered: As the ruine of ANTICHRIST, and the ſeverall degrees thereunto; And the ſhadowing out theſe times wherein we live, are generally ſurveyed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Sweeting</hi> at the <hi>Angel</hi> in <hi>Popes-head Alley,</hi> 1651.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:112152:2"/>
            <head>The Stationer to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL that I have to ſay, is, That this brief Expoſition of that Religious and Learned Divine Mr. <hi>Robert Parker,</hi> upon the pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring out of the foure laſt Vialls mentioned in the ſixteen chap. of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> hath been for this many yeers (before the <hi>Palatinat</hi> was reduced to a field of blood) in the cuſtody of Sir <hi>Iohn Wray,</hi> to whoſe piety thou ſtandeſt engaged for the publicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: the Author was eſteemed pious and learned, a Non-conformiſt to the Biſhops. Happily he may dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer in opinion from Mr. <hi>Brightman</hi> and other learned men, but that is no wonder; for they could not agree among themſelves: I have done my part, the Copy was ſent mee to procure a paſſage into the Publick, the which is performed; and by the way, that as the worthy Gentleman that gave me the <hi>Manuſcript</hi> and the <hi>Imprimatur</hi> thought it worthy the printing; I cannot think otherway but that it deſerves the buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="exposition">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:112152:2"/>
            <head>THE MYSTERY OF THE VIALLS OPENED.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>REVEL. 16.8, 9.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And the fourth Angel poured out his viall upon the Sun, and power was given him to ſcorch men with fire.</p>
                  <p>And men were ſcorched with great heat, and blaſphemed the name of God, which hath power over theſe plagues: and they repented not to give him glory.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lthough I am not worthy to bee named with Mr. <hi>Brightman,</hi> yet I truſt I may crave leave under correction, to differ from him, in the Expoſition of this Viall. I proſecute his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory with all the benediction that is due to ſo great a light in the Church of God, and hold himſelf (for cleering this Apocalyps) the chief Angell of this Viall, in caſe it bee meant of Proteſtant writers (as he would have it) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Scriptures as cleer as the Sun, to the confounding and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting of Papiſts; howbeit there be ſome reaſons, that lead mee to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:112152:3"/>
interpret it rather of the waſting of ſome Proteſtant Princes or <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran</hi> State not long hence to be accompliſhed, which I crave liberty to ſet down.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The confounding and tormenting of Papiſts by the Scripture, is not a diſtinct particular event, as the event of this fourth Viall ſeems to be Diſtinct it is not, but the ſame with the plague of the firſt Viall, whoſe botch, what is it elſe but an ulcer of mind in Papiſts to ſee the growth of the Goſpel, and fall of Popery, eſpecially here at home in <hi>England</hi> by the death of Qu. <hi>Mary,</hi> and the ſucceſſion of Qu. <hi>Eliz.</hi> to the crown? And again it is generall, whereas the Viall is poured on the Sun a particular ſtar in heaven, to note a plague on ſome ſpeciall State of ſome true Church, or at leaſt ſome Church diſunited from Popery.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Sun being King amongſt ſtars, <hi>Jer.</hi> 44.17. he fitly here defineth ſome King or State even as he doth elſewhere, ſo <hi>Jacob</hi> (the moſt heroicall man in his dayes) is reſembled by the Sun, <hi>Gen.</hi> 37. <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.17. and <hi>Hezekiah</hi> King of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 20.9, 10. Who is the Angel ſtanding in the Sun? <hi>Apoc.</hi> 19.17. out of doubt ſome great man in power and place; foraſmuch as the writing of ſome bare Divines cannot ſo effectually draw People and Nations to join in war againſt the Pope; What is that darkning of the Sunne? <hi>Apoc.</hi> 6.12. the fall of the perſecuting <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, and the third part of the Sun ſmitten, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 8.12. is the waſting of <hi>Africa</hi> the third part of the world by the <hi>Vandalls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. In this fourth Viall the Sun himſelf is firſt plagued, which cannot be meant of the Scripture, for the text doth ſay as directly that the fourth Angell doth poure his Viall on the Sun, as the fift doth poure his Viall on the throne of the beaſt, by which <hi>Romes</hi> ruine is foreſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: Howbeit the Sun not extinguiſhed by this Viall but only diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered to ſcorch with heat, doth ſeem to imploy that the plague of this Prince or State ſhall not caſt them down ſo much, as irritate and ſtirre them up to a heat of revenge, laying waſte the men that did hurt them.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The men here plagued are not only Papiſts, for whereas it is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to them in the firſt Viall by way of reſtraint, that the ſore fell up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them which had the mark of the beaſt and who worſhiped his image; here is no ſuch limitation; it is only ſaid in generall, power was given to the Sun to torment men, <hi>viz.</hi> men of the ſame heaven where the Sun ſhineth, <hi>viz.</hi> men in that viſible Church where this Prince or State doth governe: Nevertheleſſe there is hope given that the godly of this Church ſhall eſcape in that that being ſaid of the plagued, they gave not glory to God; there is probability that this judgement ſhall only light on the Papiſts, or at the leaſt, chiefly, and wicked men mingled with this Eſtate and Church, who before had no care of Gods glory or the Goſpels good, but only ſought their own glory, wealth and pleaſures.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The plague here deſcribed is not only by heat, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> yet were ſufficient to uphold the alluſion of the Sun, but alſo by fire; this maketh me con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jecture
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:112152:3"/>
that this Prince or State ſhall lay deſolate by fire and burning more then by ſword, God girding him or them with ſuch power, as that they ſhall not need to fight many battails; neither ought it to ſeem ſtrange, that fire here meant laying all things waſte ſhould literally be meant, ſeeing the Angell that hath power over this fire, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 14.18. is <hi>Cranmer</hi> triumphing in the fire of Martyrdom; &amp; the burning of the fleſh of the Whore, is the ſacking of <hi>Rome, Apoc.</hi> 17.16. ſo the Angell of the Waters in the 5<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> 
               <hi>verſ.</hi> going before, reſembleth the States of the <hi>Low Germany</hi> ſeated in a watry Countrey.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The effect of this plague in the wicked is boiling in heat, and gnawing of their tongues, and blaſpheming the name of God, which contain more then an inward rage of Papiſts, for the confounding of their Religion by the Scriptures; they muſt needs ſhew welneer ſuch a ruine of State as the ruin of <hi>Rome</hi> comes to: foraſmuch as great a plague is deſcribed here as in the firſt Vial, and that in the ſame terms and words, as appeareth by comparing the 9 <hi>verſ.</hi> with the 11 follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: add to this, that the plague of this Viall is uttered in the plurall number, they blaſphemed the name of God over theſe plagues, as if it contained many confuſions in it; and this anſwereth to the juſtice of God, who beginneth judgment at his own houſe, and at them who make profeſſion to be of his houſhold. By this <hi>Revelation</hi> the Pope ſhall be deſtroyed before the <hi>Turke,</hi> becauſe he profeſſed Chriſtianity, which the <hi>Turkes</hi> did not. In like manner before God deſtroy the <hi>Pope,</hi> hee ſhall pour out his Viall on ſome <hi>Proteſtant</hi> or <hi>Lutheran</hi> Church which made profeſſion of the Goſpel againſt Popery, but obeyed it not: by this means it ſhall come to paſſe what was done of old; then God afflicted <hi>Jewry</hi> his own Church, before he deſtroyed the earthly <hi>Babylon;</hi> now he ſhall puniſh one of his own Churches, before hee proceed againſt <hi>Rome</hi> the ſpirituall <hi>Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. I conjecture, that this Sun of the fourth Viall puniſhing a rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Church, and the Angell of the fifth Viall ſacking <hi>Rome,</hi> is all one and the ſame: Firſt, becauſe the fifth Viall is immediately adjoined and expreſſed with the very ſame tearms, which probably induceth to think that it ſhall be wrought by the ſame means: this conjecture is helped by this, that the rebelling againſt the Sun of the fourth Viall, ſhall be procured by the Pope and Papiſt, which ſhall be in caſe that this Sun, ſo ſoon as he hath ſubdued his domeſticall enemies, ſhall addreſſe himſelf to an Expedition againſt <hi>Rome:</hi> Secondly, the ruin of <hi>Rome</hi> ariſeth from a wilderneſs, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 17.3. Firſt, as I conjecture, out of the ſame Countrey laid waſte like a wilderneſs. This Countrey muſt be the State waſted by the Sun of the fourth Viall, for we have no Prophecy of any other State to be laid waſte, immediately before <hi>Romes</hi> ſacking, but only of that: now that <hi>John</hi>'s carrying into the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſee the ruine of <hi>Rome,</hi> doth ſhew that <hi>Romes</hi> ruine ſhall ariſe out of a land, brought to a wilderneſs, may thus appear. Wherefore is <hi>John</hi> ſet on the ſea ſhore, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 12.18. when he is to ſee the riſing of the Beaſt,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:112152:4"/>
but becauſe of the beaſts riſing out of the ſea, <hi>ergo,</hi> in that <hi>John Apoc.</hi> 17.3. is placed in a wilderneſſe to ſee <hi>Romes</hi> ruine, it is a ſign that <hi>Romes</hi> ruine ſhall riſe out of ſome Countrey reduced to a wilderneſſe. So when <hi>Iohn</hi> is to ſee the beauty of the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> Church, he is carryed to a great high mountain to ſee it. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21.10. <hi>i. e.</hi> becauſe his Church ſhall be ſet up on high like to a mountain, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22.3. This is the deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of him which ſacketh <hi>Rome, Apoc.</hi> 18.1. I ſaw a great Angell come down from heaven, having great power, ſo that the earth was enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with his glory, which agreeth with the Sun of this fourth Viall: he cometh down from heaven; Firſt, ſuddenly beyond all expectation of man; Secondly, the Sun of the fourth Viall ariſeth ſuddenly out of his plague, when the world thought he could never have recovered, he hath great power given him, this is the power of the Sun of the fourth Viall, both by glory of conquering, and the wealth of the conquered, which he ſhall get into his hands: he hath light and brightneſs, which what is it elſe but the Sunne of the fourth Viall his light and brightneſs? Laſtly, hee repleniſheth the earth with his glory; which implyeth the great admiration of the world, and the aſtoniſhment of Papiſts and earthly men; when they ſhall ſee the Sun of the fourth Viall ariſe ſo extraordinarily out of his plague. Fourthly, and laſt of all, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 17.16. it is ſaid, that the ten hornes ſhall ſack <hi>Rome:</hi> and who ſhall the States of Chriſtendome ſooner chooſe for their Generall or proclaime their Emperour againſt <hi>Rome,</hi> then he that hath been plagued by Papiſts, and enraged againſt them, and furniſhed with greateſt authority, power and wealth to ſubdue them?</p>
            <p>Thus have I preſumed to deliver my conjecture concerning this fourth Viall; I ſay conjecture, becauſe it cannot certainly be known, till it bee executed: Nevertheleſs, becauſe the time thereof approacheth it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh every Chriſtian man to ſtrive by prayer, meditation, ſtudy, and all other means for ſome underſtanding of it, conſidering that he hath not writ this propheſie only to inſtruct us when it is paſt, but alſo to forewarn us even aforehand.</p>
            <p>The Revealer of ſecrets that unſealed this book to <hi>John,</hi> open unto us the myſtery of it, that we may foreſee the evill that is to come, and hide our ſelves from it: as alſo keep our ſelves pure from offences againſt our Sun, leſt we partake of the plagues which this Viall doth denounce againſt all ſuch tranſgreſſions. To God only wiſe be honor and glory for ever, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="exposition">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:112152:4"/>
            <head>Mr. <hi>Parker</hi> his Meditations of the Reign of ANTICHRIST, and of ſeverall degrees thereunto. OR, A ſhort and generall Survey of the three laſt VIALLS, in all probabilities no leſſe plainly then admirably ſhadowing out theſe times wherein we live, out of REVEL. 6.10.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE extraordinary accidents that happen within the chriſtian world in theſe our days being without doubt pointed at in that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall hiſtory of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> cannot but inforce a ſerious muſing of the period of theſe combuſtions, the truth of which the event will admirably diſcover, being though ſomewhat darkly ſhadowed forth in this Chapter; The deſire of the true meaning whereof have made theſe thoughts legible. You have heard in the opening of the fourth Viall, a preparation to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Romes</hi> ruine; the Viall poured upon the ſun, <hi>i. e.</hi> ſome ſharp ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamity and affliction falling upon ſome <hi>Proteſtant</hi> or <hi>Lutheran</hi> Prince, aſſuredly ſome State diſunited from Popery. This Sun recovering him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from his plague, which may laſt for ſome yeers in all probability, not above ten, ſhal make an expedition againſt his oppreſſors, ſcorching the popelings with the heat of miſery in the fury of anger. And thus far goes the fourth Viall.</p>
            <p>This Sun or Prince being recovered from his plague; thinks that not a ſufficient revenge to devour and burn the inferiour members of the adverſe party, intendeth an expedition, prepareth a warre againſt the head, the abettors and ſetters on of the inflictors of his plague, which is plainly ſhadowed out by the fift Viall, as you ſhall hear.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And the fift Angell poured out his Viall on the throne of the Beaſt, and his Kingdom was full of darkneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here is a more direct ſtriking at the head, then in the former Viall,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:112152:5"/>
for in other things there is a great reſemblance betwixt theſe two Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls, they both exerciſe their extremity againſt men, they both cauſe blaſpheming of God in their adverſaries, which doth ſtrongly confirm the conjecture that you heard of in the former Viall, that the Sun of the fourth Viall, and the Angel of the fifth Viall is all one and the ſame man, in a double warlike expedition; for firſt, having the Viall poured upon himſelfe, he lies for a certain time hidden and obſcured, as though his light and heat had been utterly darkned, and cooled; and riſing out of his miſery, he ſhall ſcorch ſome petty Armies with the heat of his anger, perhaps overcoming that Army, that before gave him the foil, ſpoiling thoſe neighbour territories that had made a prey of his, during his darkneſs, and lying in his plague, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ſhal cauſe his adverſaries to fret, and curſe, and ban, that a halfe dead man ſhould thus ſtrangely ariſe, and to their everlaſting ſhame and overthrow become potent: But now coming to a higher pitch, attended with greater ſtrength, ſhall caſt his thoughts upon higher things, the effecting of greater matters, even the overthrow of the head of rebells, the Antichriſtian beaſt, the <hi>Romiſh</hi> whore. We ſee then who this fift Angell is: In all likelyhood, ſome Prince or State an enemy to Popery, recovering health after a long ſickneſſe, peace after many troubles, and ſtrength after great weakneſſe, whereinto he was caſt, by the cruell tyranny of the beaſts members. Having thus found out the party, let us look upon his work: he pours ſaith the text, his Viall upon the throne of the beaſt; the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratives thus far fitly concurring, <hi>viz. Romes</hi> deſtroyer, being ſet on his feet, and made Maſter of his domeſticall enemies, he ſends a defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance againſt the head, and pours out his wrath upon the principall; And here I muſt crave leave to differ again in my conjecture from the ſun of this age Mr. <hi>Brightman,</hi> as I ſhall doe in all theſe three laſt Vialls, and that not without reaſon, as in the opening of them ſhall appear. For whereas Mr. <hi>Brightman</hi> doth put a full period to Antichriſt his reign in this fifth Viall; I cannot ſee how that can be, foraſmuch as there fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows in the next Viall things which muſt neceſſarily praecede <hi>Romes</hi> ruine. We may therefore with more reaſon, and no derogation of praiſe due to ſo worthy a lamp, refer its deſolation to the ſeventh Viall, &amp; make this a more neer and cleer preparative thereunto. This Angel then bearing an inward hatred to the Whore, ſhall uſe all means to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throne her from her chaire of State, to eclipſe her glory, to darken her brightneſs; but not daring as yet to meddle with the head and principal parts, he ſhall clip her wings that ſhe dare not ſore too high, put bounds to her Dominions, diſpoſſeſſe her of ſome parts of her Kingdoms, for in that it is ſaid her Kingdome was darkened, or did wax darke, not was overthrown; it is plaine that this is only an abridging her of her large morſells, obſcuring her brightneſſe, pulling ſome fair feathers out of her proud train, making her to view her black legs, the baſeneſs of her riſing, that ſhe ſhall not dare to vaunt her ſelf as the prime darlings amongſt the ſons of the Children of Pride: This makes me conjecture
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:112152:5"/>
that this Angell, this Prince or State ſhall get ſome of the temporall Kingdomes of Antichriſt out of the claws of this Beaſt to himſelfe; whereby the extent of her rule ſhall be ſtraightned: And if I ſhould thinke that this Angell of the fift Viall (being that ſame afflicted Sun in the fourth Viall) ſhall bee elected the head of the ten hornes that ſhall ſack <hi>Rome,</hi> of whom we will ſpeak more in the next Viall; the reſemblance that is between the probable events of this election, and the effects of this Viall will warrant the conjecture; for weigh them a little; Firſt, if this Angell be choſen Head or Emperour, in all likelyhood, nay without all doubt hee will ſcorn to receive the Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Crown from the paw of the Beaſt, who is his mortall enemy; and is not this a ſhroud darkneſſe to the Beaſts vainglorious authority; for without controverſie, the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Beaſt doth glory in nothing more then this, that ſhee hath power to ſet up, and to pull downe, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throne and dethrone, to crown and uncrown Emperours and Kings at her pleaſure, which power all her Worſhippers and Flatterers doe give her, as is plain in their writings to be ſeen: Now then this jug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling deceit of hers, or rather tyrannicall uſurpation of authority over the <hi>Germane</hi> Emperours, being diſcovered and diſpelled, neglected and contemned, her eſteem will be much diminiſhed, her reputation ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſhed, her brightneſſe obſcured, her vain threats, and childiſh thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbolts of Excommunication derided; and may not this loſſe of crowning Kings bee well ſaid to bee a darkning of her King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome?</p>
            <p>Moreover, adde hereunto a ſecond degree of darkneſſe: This An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell being choſen Emperour and Head, ſhall in his own perſon, or be a means that he that is the Head ſhal wring the whole <hi>German</hi> Empire out of this Beaſts clutches; for there is no likelyhood, but that hee that in deſpite of the Beaſt is recovered out of his plague, ſhall to ſpite the Beaſt draw all his own ſubjects from the obedience of this Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an tyrant, which thing being ſuch a wide gap into the Beaſts power, may well be called a darkening of his Kingdome; and in theſe two things eſpecially the Emperors refuſing to be crowned, or to receive his Dominion from the Pope, and the wreſting, or rather freeing of the whole <hi>Germane</hi> Empire from Popiſh ſlavery, ſhall the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the fifth Viall be accompliſhed; for ſtill remember, that this Angell at this time ſhall darken, not overturn the Kingdome of the beaſt (which thing Mr. <hi>Brightman</hi> in part did ſee) it being as cleare as the ſun, that the darkning of the Beaſts Kingdom, implies a declina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not a deſolation, a falling <hi>a tanto,</hi> not <hi>a toto,</hi> an eclipſing of her glorious luſtre, not an extinguiſhing of her whole body: Neither need this to move any doubt; becauſe the Viall is poured upon the ſeat or throne of the Beaſt which is <hi>Rome,</hi> and therefore ought we to expect the accompliſhment of this Viall on that City. For I anſwer it is plain, and our uſuall manner of ſpeech to call the whole Kingdome the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:112152:6"/>
throne of the King, or the ſeat of the Governour; and ſo the throne of Antichriſt is every where, where he is eſteemed and worſhipped; for though this Angell ſhall have a good mind to bee medling with the Beaſts perſon, and in all likelyhood he, or ſome of his ſhall be the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Angell that ſhall make an end of her, yet ſhall he not in the time of this fifth Viall dare to attempt ſo high a deſigne, but ſhall for a while content himſelfe to have freed himſelfe and his Empire from the ſlaviſh bondage of <hi>Romiſh</hi> tyranny, deferring his expedition againſt <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Beaſt, untill that potent, proper, and mighty upholder, of their ruinous and tottering eſtate ſhall be broken and removed, which the ſixt angel ſhal ere long diſcover and take away, as in the opening of that ſhall appear.</p>
            <p>You have ſeen this angell and his Viall; now let us look what fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes upon this, how the Beaſt and his followers take this blow, for ſurely ſuch a great blemiſh cannot but move them, at leaſt to ſome paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate behaviour againſt their oppreſſor; now this effect is the ſame that followed the ſcorching of the Sun in the fourth Viall, that differs only in degree, for the nearer the blow comes to the head, and the more eminent that the expedition of this (not long ſince forlorne man) is, the more is their pain, the greater is their rage; for if they did blaſpheme God when the Sun did but ſcorch the baſer, and meaneſt pillars in the Popes Church: What will they do now when he comes to take away the main pillar whereupon the building of Popery hangs, and the corner ſtone in their church? Why, the text ſhews, <hi>They gnawed their tongues for paines.</hi> Theſe are the Beaſts attendants; before they vented their diſcontent againſt God in more mild ſort; but now they are even mad with rage, and like mad men they tear their own fleſh.</p>
            <p>The Beaſts friends and followers ſhall be ſo aſtoniſhed at this wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full alteration, that becauſe they ſhall want power to give their fury vent againſt their enemies, they ſhall wreak that upon themſelves, at the conſideration of this ſudden and unexpected accident; and certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly this is more then probable, that the popelings ſhall be in this raging fit of madneſſe, at this ſo extraordinary darkning of their Kingdom; for as they exulting over, and trampling upon this Sun, this afflicted State in time of his plague did falſly and fondly flatter themſelves with dreams of perpetual reſt, becauſe the hater of their tyrany was ſuppreſt; even ſo, they ſeing this worm (for ſo he was in their conceits) lift up his head againſt his adverſaries, ſhall be moved; but when they ſee him confront their authority, enforce their ſwelling waves to keep within their owne channell; Oh then they ſhall bee enraged. The darkning of their Kingdome doth much move them; but that it ſhould be darkned by this State, this beyond meaſure ſets them on fire; here is blaſpheming, curſing, gnawing, What not? for aſſuredly, this ſo ſudden, unlooked for, ſtrange encreaſe of this angell, ſhall gall at the very heart all the ſwarms of Monkes, Friers, Jeſuites, Cardinalls, and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:112152:6"/>
the reſt of the rabble of this Antichriſtian crew: For this darkning of their Kingdome is ſuch a pain and ſore to them (for theſe words the Holy-ghoſt gives it) as nothing can bee greater, and well it may when all the pains that they have taken in masking Antichriſt, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering him under the vaile of their Inventions ſhall be proved but ſmoak. But what, doth this diſcovery of their falſities, theſe pains drive them to the truth? Nay ſaith the Spirit, both in the former and in this Viall, they repented not, &amp;c. Whence I conjecture, that few or none, in reſpect of the generality of the grand and head Papiſts, not many of the Beaſts followers ſhall be drawn out of their wilfull blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the damnation of this <hi>Romiſh</hi> where, but ſhall receive their reward at one hour, in one manner with the Beaſt.</p>
            <p>Thus have wee in ſpight of the Beaſt, and without his conſent, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throned this angell in his place appointed, from which he ſhall never deſcend, till he hath executed againſt <hi>Rome</hi> the judgement that is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten: for yet a little while and their deſtruction ſhall come as an ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med man; which cannot bee, till that which upholdeth her bee taken out of the way, which the ſixth angell with his Viall will ſpeedily do; Thus far the fifth Viall.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="exposition">
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>VER. 12.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And the ſixt Angell poured out his Viall upon the great River <hi>Euphrates</hi> and the water thereof was dryed up.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>Wee mentioned in the former Vyall, a certain potent prop that did uphold the Beaſt, and kept the fift angell a while from bringing a finall deſolation to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Beaſt, which obſtacle, both what it was, and the means of its removall, wee have here plainly diſcovered.</p>
            <p>And here though I take Mr. <hi>Brightman</hi> to be under God a principall angell in this Vyall alſo, in caſe it be meant of the converſion of the <hi>Jews</hi> as he would have it, in that he hath ſet the pens, tongues, and hearts of many on work, in the opening of this opinion, which is ſo plainly and firmly grounded on the Word of God, that I think it impoſſible to be infringed, and doe alſo without all queſtion beleeve it ſhall be effected in its time; yet notwithſtanding, I neither doe nor can think that this eminent worke was aimed at any whit at all in this verſe; my reaſons are theſe:</p>
            <p>Firſt, this drying up of <hi>Euphrates</hi> comes in the time of <hi>Romes</hi> decli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, but before her finall deſolation, but the man of Sinne ſhall bee utterly aboliſhed, at the brightneſſe of Chriſts coming to call the <hi>Jews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the end of this Rivers drying up, is to make a way for the Kings of the <hi>Eaſt;</hi> implying, that theſe Kings ſhall come up all one way together, about one buſineſſe; and the originall <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the way, imports as much, which way was barred up to all theſe <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Princes
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:112152:7"/>
alike, by the current of this River: but the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhall be converted from all the four winds; ſo that this River can onely hinder one part of them, What comfort can the <hi>Weſtern Jews</hi> have from hence?</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the converſion of the <hi>Jews</hi> is deſcribed in whole Chapters afterwards; it is not likely then the Spirit of God would either include that ſo briefly and darkly here, which in more words he doth plainly open afterwards, or that he would inſert it here in the midſt of the Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls, and after without any method come back again: I rather think that from hence to the end of <hi>Revelation</hi> is an orderly and methodicall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of things that ſhall happen to the end of the world, ſome few digreſſions only excepted.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, if the converſion of the <hi>Jews</hi> be here meant, then is the drying up of <hi>Euphrates</hi> literally meant, which is not uſuall in this book, eſpecially in ſuch paſſages of note and eminencie; to ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of this, that the truth of this miracle hath no ſure foundation I think in the Book of God, but only ſome propheticall alluſions, and the propheſie of the counterfeit <hi>Eſdras</hi> in the <hi>Apocrypha.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This interpretation therefore not holding water, wee muſt ſee for ſome other;</p>
            <p>I conjecture then by the drying up of <hi>Euphrates</hi> is underſtood the removall of that obſtacle which is an impediment to the Expedition of the fifth angell againſt the Beaſt himſelfe: Now what this impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diment was, we ſhall find out, if we ſeriouſly conſider the thing it ſelfe under which it is ſhadowed.</p>
            <p>What is then <hi>Euphrates?</hi> for this being once known, we ſhall the more eaſily gather who ſhall be this angell that poures out his Viall upon <hi>Euphrates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euphrates</hi> then is a River (to ſay ſo much of it as concerns our purpoſe) in <hi>Caldea</hi> that runs through that great City <hi>Babylon,</hi> and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formes to that City a double office, the one of maintenance, for upon that River is brought all kind of merchandize, whereby the State of the City is upheld, the other of defence, being as a wall to the City, and a ſure ſafeguard to the Citizens, inſomuch that the inhabitants had a certain confidence (which for the ſure beleef thereof ſome have termed a Propheſie) that they ſhould never be overcome till the River prove their enemy.</p>
            <p>Now when <hi>Cyrus</hi> King of <hi>Perſia</hi> came againſt the City, and beſieged it a long time, but in vain, he did by divers new made channells divert the courſe of the water, and through the old channell being now made drie, he entred the City, and got <hi>Babylon;</hi> and ſo was their confidence or Propheſie made true, the River became their enemy, and made a way for this <hi>Perſian</hi> Prince.</p>
            <p>Thus wee ſee what <hi>Euphrates</hi> was, by which wee may be warranted to think, that by <hi>Euphrates</hi> here is meant ſome State or Kingdome, which is to <hi>Rome</hi> as <hi>Euphrates</hi> was to <hi>Babylon,</hi> a ſupporter and defence:
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:112152:7"/>
Now when I thought of all the States and Princes in this <hi>Weſtern</hi> world, I ſee none a greater ſupporter to the ſeat of Antichriſt, or more ſtands for him, then doth the Catholique King (as the Popelings call him) I conjecture therefore, that by <hi>Euphrates</hi> in this verſe is meant the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and State of the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> for doe but weigh them, and you ſhall ſee how fully they agree.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Euphrates</hi> is a great River in <hi>Caldea,</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> is a great Kingdome in <hi>Europa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Euphrates</hi> did convey maintenance to <hi>Babylon,</hi> and ſo did uphold the City, and it is notoriouſly remarkable, that <hi>Spain</hi> is the ſole nouriſher and upholder of the Popiſh Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Euphrates</hi> was a defence to <hi>Babylon,</hi> and who knowes not that the Beaſt of <hi>Rome</hi> doth acknowledge the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> forces to be the only ſupporters of his credit, the bar that keeps his enemies from trampling his triple crown in the duſt.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Babylon</hi> could not be won, nor <hi>Cyrus</hi> have any way into that City, till the water of this River was dryed up, and may wee not well thinke, that the only cauſe that ſtayes the fift Angel, and other <hi>Eaſterne</hi> Princes from an Expedition againſt <hi>Rome,</hi> is the power of <hi>Spain,</hi> for they ſhall ſtand waiting till this current of ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation that runs from <hi>Spain</hi> to <hi>Rome</hi> bee dryed up, and <hi>Spain</hi> enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to beſtow their ſtrength elſewhere, perhaps in their owne de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence.</p>
            <p>But who ſhall bee this ſixt Angell that ſhall poure his Viall upon <hi>Euphrates?</hi> Why ſurely I think this will give a great probability to my former conjecture; To poure out the Viall, in all this <hi>Revela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> doth ſignifie to lay affliction upon, and bring miſery unto, and moſt uſually the plague of War; ſome Prince therefore, or State ſhall fall at oddes with <hi>Spain,</hi> and hold her play at home, that ſhee ſhall not attend to ſuccour her ancient friend, the Beaſt, and his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers.</p>
            <p>And if I ſhould think that this State or ſixth Angell ſhall bee the Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> or the <hi>Low countreys,</hi> or both jointly with their friends; one peradventure would think it unlikely, and yet the next age, or perhaps this will (it may he) make it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that they ſhall have a principall hand in pouring out this ſixth Viall.</p>
            <p>But who are thoſe <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Kings whoſe way by this meanes ſhall bee prepared, and what is this preparation of their way to doe?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, Even the ſame men, that are afterwards called the Ten hornes prepared in a readineſſe to ſack <hi>Rome,</hi> who are both here and there called Kings; and yet <hi>chap.</hi> 17. are ſaid to have no crownes, which in my conceit doth moſt admirably ſhadow out the <hi>German</hi> Princes, every of which is an abſolute Prince in his owne
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:112152:8"/>
territory, and therefore may well be called a King, yet are not crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; they have not the name of Kings, but have a head, as theſe horns had, which bears the crown, the name over them all, even the Emperour, which at this time ſhall bee Angell of the fifth Viall; for theſe Princes and their head is it, that this way is prepared; for they ſeeing that <hi>Romes Euphrates,</hi> her ſupporter is dryed up, ſhall preſently joine in an Expedition, which ſhall bee the finall deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this purple Whore, wee ſee now the meaning.</p>
            <p>The ſixt Angell poured out his Viall upon <hi>Euphrates,</hi> and the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters thereof were dryed up, that the wayes of the Kings of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> might be prepared, <hi>i. e. England,</hi> or the <hi>Low countries,</hi> or ſome other Prince enemy to <hi>Spain,</hi> doth fall at oddes with <hi>Spain,</hi> by which <hi>Spain</hi> is enforced to imploy his forces for his own defence, and ſuffereth his aid, which he was uſed to ſend to <hi>Romes</hi> help to bee dryed up; which occaſion the <hi>Germane</hi> Princes, and their Head laying hold upon, and finding their way fitly prepared, becauſe <hi>Rome</hi> is now left deſtitute of forrain help, execute that for which they were kept to be ready at a day or an houre, when the Lord ſhould call; where by the way we may note, how the Lord makes all things admirably concurre to his own ends. The Jars betwixt this ſixt Angell and <hi>Euphrates</hi> is for this end, to make a way open for the <hi>Germane</hi> Princes to ſack <hi>Rome;</hi> Whereupon I conjecture and verily think, that all the troubles that ſhall happen in this <hi>Weſtern</hi> world in theſe times, are only to make way, for the ruine of <hi>Rome,</hi> upon whoſe head, and in whoſe ruine they ſhall at the laſt all fall and end now: let us in a word look upon that which followes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And I ſaw three unclean ſpirits, &amp;c.</hi> That which remains of this Viall in the three next verſes is only thus much: That the Pope per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving his eſtate to decline, his Kingdome and authority to totter, himſelfe left deſtitute and forſaken of his deareſt and only ſon the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> his fierce enemies now, ſometimes his vaſſalls, plotting, ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gining, affecting his overthrow, ſhall by the inſtigation of the great dragon, the devill, and the perſwaſion of the falſe Prophets his flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring crew of Cardinalls, Friers, and the reſt of that Antichriſtian building, ſend forth his croaking Jeſuites, who ſhall by their crafty ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilneſſe goe forth unto the Kings of the earth, incite and ſtir them up to take in hand the defence of their maſter Antichriſt, whoſe ruin then is coming, and ſhall fall unexſpectedly and ſuddenly upon him, as by that ſudden digreſſion and exclamation, <hi>Behold I come as a thiefe, &amp;c.</hi> may be gathered; when theſe frogs have gathered what Kings they can together, by whoſe ſtrength their maſter this beaſt expects a reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, at leaſt a prolongation of his former glory, hee ſhall unlooked for receive his fatall wound, which ſhall make him irrecoverably ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire; for then,</p>
            <p>Verſ. 17. <hi>The ſeventh Angell pours out his Viall upon the aire, and a
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:112152:8"/>
great voice comes forth of the Temple, ſaying, It is done, &amp;c.</hi> Here is the utter deſolation of <hi>Rome,</hi> and the tyranny thereof preſaged, and not of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> which ſhall come to his finall period in the overthrow of Gog, not now; In the mean ſpace let us with our prayers cry mightily unto God, that this Man of Sinne may not long oppreſſe;</p>
            <closer>Which God grant.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
